<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://qgevoeco.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://qgevoeco.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-10-26T09:54:01+02:00</updated><id>https://qgevoeco.github.io/atom.xml</id><title type="html">Quantitative Genetic Evolutionary Ecology</title><subtitle>The Wolak Research Group at Auburn University.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Summer 2020 NSF Aquatic Ecology Research Experience for Undergraduates</title><link href="https://qgevoeco.github.io/news/NSF-REU-aquaticEcology/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Summer 2020 NSF Aquatic Ecology Research Experience for Undergraduates" /><published>2019-10-12T15:04:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-10-12T15:04:00+02:00</updated><id>https://qgevoeco.github.io/news/NSF-REU-aquaticEcology</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://qgevoeco.github.io/news/NSF-REU-aquaticEcology/">&lt;h4 id=&quot;application-deadline-february-1-2020&quot;&gt;Application Deadline February 1, 2020&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Auburn University is again hosting a US National Science Foundation &lt;a href=&quot;http://wilsonlab.com/reu/index.html&quot;&gt;warm-water aquatic ecology REU&lt;/a&gt;. Our group is hosting a project and looking for enthusiastic applicants. You can see all of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://wilsonlab.com/reu/projects.html&quot;&gt;projects&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://wilsonlab.com/reu/mentors.html&quot;&gt;mentors&lt;/a&gt;, but the description of our project is &lt;strong&gt;Freshwater turtle population ecology and evolutionary patterns&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This project will focus on population-wide patterns of survival and reproduction and link these to broader patterns in morphology within- and among-species of freshwater turtles. The REU student will work closely with the mentors to create data driven population models and conduct statistical analyses. The student will also have ample opportunity to participate in ongoing field research on several turtle species found in water bodies around Auburn. The student will develop their quantitative skill set by learning several modeling and statistical analysis techniques, learn how to capture and process freshwater turtles, and gain experience designing analyses based on ecological and evolutionary hypotheses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See this recent News item about our &lt;a href=&quot;/news/JorgeREUposter2019&quot;&gt;REU project with Jorge&lt;/a&gt; this past summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:mjj0028@auburn.edu&quot;&gt;contact Maria Joao&lt;/a&gt; if you are interested!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="science" /><category term="NSF" /><category term="REU" /><category term="research" /><category term="undergraduate" /><category term="ecology" /><summary type="html">Call for Auburn NSF REU applications</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://qgevoeco.github.io/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22nsf-logo.png%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Turtle Week Fall 2019</title><link href="https://qgevoeco.github.io/news/turtle-week-fall2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Turtle Week Fall 2019" /><published>2019-09-23T14:24:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-09-23T14:24:00+02:00</updated><id>https://qgevoeco.github.io/news/turtle-week-fall2019</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://qgevoeco.github.io/news/turtle-week-fall2019/">&lt;p&gt;I just wrapped up the innagural AU Turtle Week, in which we integrated some of our group’s research with teaching in the &lt;em&gt;Principles of Ecology&lt;/em&gt; course this fall. About 80 undergraduate students and 5 Graduate Teaching Assistants came together at one of the ponds on campus for a intensive 8 days of turtle capture, marking, measuring, and release. Altogether, we caught 5 different species of turtle (in order of abundance, &lt;em&gt;Trachemys scripta&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Chrysemys picta&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Sternotherus odoratus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Kinosternon subrubrum&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Chelydra serpentina&lt;/em&gt;), averaging about 6 individuals per day. The students will work out population size estimates for &lt;em&gt;T. scripta&lt;/em&gt; over the next week, but this was a really great effort by all and the start of what I hope will be a long-term dataset for researchers and students to both use in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;

  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/snapperChad20190914-600-2d228a.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Student holding a common snapping turtle&quot; /&gt;

  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/turtleWeek20190918-600-46b6bf.webp&quot; alt=&quot;TA guiding students on how to measure turtles&quot; /&gt;

  &lt;figurecaption&gt;Only 1 common snapping turtle (first picture), processed without incident. Students teamed up (second picture) to measure turtles, each student specializing in just 1 or 2 measurements.&lt;/figurecaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;

  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/turtleWeek20190917-600-1ee65c.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Students holding tiny juvenile turtle&quot; /&gt;

  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/turtleWeek20190920-600-90fc52.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Students holding another tiny juvenile turtle&quot; /&gt;

  &lt;figurecaption&gt;The smallest juveniles were the stars (of course)!&lt;/figurecaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Science" /><category term="Ecology" /><category term="turtles" /><category term="research" /><category term="teaching" /><summary type="html">Like Shark Week, but with actual science...</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://qgevoeco.github.io/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22turtleWeek-20190918.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22feature-Biol3060-turtles-20190919.png%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Destination STEM 2019</title><link href="https://qgevoeco.github.io/news/Destination-STEM-fall2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Destination STEM 2019" /><published>2019-09-21T19:24:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-09-21T19:24:00+02:00</updated><id>https://qgevoeco.github.io/news/Destination-STEM-fall2019</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://qgevoeco.github.io/news/Destination-STEM-fall2019/">&lt;p&gt;The Wolak Research Group was well represented at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.auburn.edu/cosam/departments/outreach/programs/Destination%20STEM/index.htm&quot;&gt;Destination STEM&lt;/a&gt; this year and I think the event was a great success! About 1,100 students from 18 middle and high schools near Auburn, came to the AU Coliseum to explore, interact, and learn about STEM fields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our own Molly Caldwell was on hand as part of the table by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.auburn.edu/cosam/departments/outreach/programs/SWSM/index.htm&quot;&gt;COSAM Women in Sciences and Mathematics&lt;/a&gt;, where she had some fabulous outreach animals to share in collaboration with Debbie, her mother and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.auburn.edu/cosam/faculty/biology/folkerts_deb/index.htm&quot;&gt;Professor Emeritus&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/20190920_MollyDebbieDestSTEM-600-562563.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Molly, Debbie, and outreach animals&quot; /&gt;

  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/destSTEM19_snake-600-fae04d.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Molly unsuccesfully convinces students to hold a snake&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Molly &amp;amp; Debbie with their outreach animals (left) and Molly unsuccesfully convinces students to hold a snake (right).&lt;/figcaption&gt;

  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/DestSTEM_JakeSplain2019-600-ee015e.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Jake's video game&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Jake explains the finer points of QG video games, to a distracted audience&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our group’s own table hosted a hands-on experience measuring turtle shells to illustrate an example of what evolutionary ecologists do (at least the fun, fieldwork parts!). We combined this activity with a &lt;strong&gt;quantitative genetic video game!&lt;/strong&gt; The game is based on selection acting on between-individual differences in size. Progress through the game results in evolutionary responses to selection! Jake did a tremendous effort coding a breeding value based quantitative genetic individual based model and then spent many a late night turning a boring terminal simulation into a game that has the look and feel of the original Super Mario Bros.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://qgevoeco.github.io/images/QGoutreachGame_201909.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Preview the first two levels of the quantitative genetic video game&quot; /&gt; 
  &lt;figcaption&gt;First two levels of the game. The entire distribution of sizes in the population is depicted by all of the lighter-colored individuals. Why don't some of them make it to Darwin at the end...&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feedback from the students was positive, so stay tuned as we continue to work on the game; including efforts to make it available through a website!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Science" /><category term="outreach" /><category term="STEM" /><category term="research" /><category term="teaching" /><summary type="html">Video games that bring QG Evolutionary Ecology to students</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://qgevoeco.github.io/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22DestSTEM_Coliseum2019.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22feature-DestSTEM_20190920.png%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">NSF Postdoctoral Research Fellowships in Biology</title><link href="https://qgevoeco.github.io/news/NSF-postdoc-PRFB/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NSF Postdoctoral Research Fellowships in Biology" /><published>2019-08-22T15:04:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-08-22T15:04:00+02:00</updated><id>https://qgevoeco.github.io/news/NSF-postdoc-PRFB</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://qgevoeco.github.io/news/NSF-postdoc-PRFB/">&lt;h4 id=&quot;proposal-deadline-november-19-2019-5pm-submitters-local-time&quot;&gt;Proposal Deadline November 19, 2019 (5pm submitter’s local time)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US National Science Foundation released a program solicitation (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nsf.gov/pubs/2019/nsf19597/nsf19597.htm?WT.mc_id=USNSF_25&amp;amp;WT.mc_ev=click&quot;&gt;NSF 19-597&lt;/a&gt;) calling for applicants to the Postdoctoral Research Fellowships in Biology opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would be very interested to collaborate with anyone who wishes to propose a project with me at Auburn University. Specifically, &lt;strong&gt;Competitive Area 1. Broadening Participation of Groups Underrepresented in Biology&lt;/strong&gt; or the newly added &lt;strong&gt;Competitive Area 4. Integrative Research Investigating the Rules of Life Governing Interactions Between Genomes, Environment and Phenotypes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Through this Competitive Area, BIO aims to stimulate creative integration of diverse subdisciplines of biology using combinations of observational, experimental, theoretical, and computational approaches to discover underlying principles operating across hierarchical levels of life, from biomolecules to organisms to ecosystems. Research activities under this Rules of Life Competitive Area should lead to new understanding of how higher-order structures and functions of biological systems result from the interactions of heterogeneous biological components, as shaped by the environment and evolutionary processes, thus furthering predictive capability of how key properties and mechanisms of living systems emerge from the interactions of genomes, environments, and phenotypes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:terps@auburn.edu&quot;&gt;contact me&lt;/a&gt; if you are interested!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="science" /><category term="NSF" /><category term="postdoc" /><category term="fellowship" /><category term="job" /><summary type="html">Call for NSF Postdoc fellowship applications</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://qgevoeco.github.io/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22nsf-logo.png%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">REU poster session 2019</title><link href="https://qgevoeco.github.io/news/JorgeREUposter2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="REU poster session 2019" /><published>2019-07-28T17:24:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-07-28T17:24:00+02:00</updated><id>https://qgevoeco.github.io/news/JorgeREUposter2019</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://qgevoeco.github.io/news/JorgeREUposter2019/">&lt;p&gt;The beginning of the end of summer is here, with the 2019 Warm Water Aquatic Ecology REU final poster presentation at the Auburn University Jule Collins Smith Museum of Fine Art. The art museum was a beautiful setting for this poster session (and the museum’s pond is a spot where we took our REU student Jorge to look for turtle nests on his first day in the field here!) and all 10 presenters were well prepared and did a superb job talking about their science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/REUs_JamesWeyhenmeyerVPforResearch_credAWilson-600-779b03.webp&quot; alt=&quot;2019 Warm Water Aquatic Ecology REU students&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The 2019 Warm Water Aquatic Ecology REU students with the VP for Research James Weyhenmeyer. Photo credit: Alan Wilson&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/JorgePoster20190726-600-851b23.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Jorge at his poster&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jorge did an excellent job presenting his poster and got lucky that no one asked him about the details behind the analyses using Bayesian inference for measuring differences in variance between the canopy openness of natural and randomized nest locations… He came a long way analyzing his data and now has a taste of using R, doing linear mixed models, and Bayesian inference. He handled it all with a smile and a thumbs up, but I’m not surprised given he is undaunted by data analysis, timber rattlesnakes, summer fieldwork, and chigger bites!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posterHall_credAWilson-600-19f74a.webp&quot; alt=&quot;busy REU poster hall&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Photo credit: Alan Wilson&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/JorgePresents20190726-600-5883e9.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Jorge presents his poster&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jorge and the rest of the REUs have now left Auburn and we’ll miss them! Best of luck everyone!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="science" /><category term="NSF" /><category term="REU" /><category term="poster" /><category term="turtles" /><summary type="html">A bittersweet farewell to Jorge</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://qgevoeco.github.io/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22JorgePoster20190726.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22feature-JCSMuseum20190726.jpg%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Evolution Conference 2019</title><link href="https://qgevoeco.github.io/news/Evolution2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Evolution Conference 2019" /><published>2019-06-29T19:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-06-29T19:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://qgevoeco.github.io/news/Evolution2019</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://qgevoeco.github.io/news/Evolution2019/">&lt;p&gt;We are just back from the joint annual conference for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amnat.org/home.html&quot;&gt;American Society of Naturalists&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.evolutionsociety.org/&quot;&gt;Society for the Study of Evolution&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.systbio.org/&quot;&gt;The Society of Systematic Biologists&lt;/a&gt;. This year the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.evolutionmeetings.org/evolution-2019---providence.html&quot;&gt;conference was in Providence, RI from June 21-25&lt;/a&gt; and like always it was exhausting and invigorating at the same time! Though I think the QGEE-ers from the group (myself, Maria Joao, and Jake Botello) were all inspired and couldn’t wait to get back to work in Auburn!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/PVD_Herreshoff20190626-600-82c3c8.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Herreshoff sailboat at the PVD airport&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Herreshoff wooden boat inside the PVD airport!&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/JoaoPosterEvolution_20190622-600-ac348a.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Joao poster Evolution 2019&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Joao poster-presenting like a pro.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lightning-poster&quot;&gt;Lightning poster&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the most impressive performance at the conference goes to Joao - hands down! She presented a poster relating to the first project she is working on for her postdoc after only having started the position &lt;strong&gt;10 days earlier&lt;/strong&gt;. Not to mention, in those few days between starting and standing in front of her poster at Evolution (see picture above) she was also busy sorting out her life after an international move. The poster seemed to be a success all around and is an initial step in building on theory for the evolution of sexual dimorphism with respect to quantitative genetic variation on the autosomes and sex chromosomes. At her impressive pace, stay tuned for the paper in another month…&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="science" /><category term="evolution" /><category term="conference" /><summary type="html">The annual Evolution conference</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://qgevoeco.github.io/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22PVD_Herreshoff20190626.jpg%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Beetle Olympics!</title><link href="https://qgevoeco.github.io/news/spring2019-beetleOlympics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beetle Olympics!" /><published>2019-04-24T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-04-24T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://qgevoeco.github.io/news/spring2019-beetleOlympics</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://qgevoeco.github.io/news/spring2019-beetleOlympics/">&lt;p&gt;Cue the music - we had the first ever Beetle Olympics in the lab today. We were all winners, but some people were certainly more accurate at weighing and identifying the sex of a beetle or faster at counting out 5 petri dishes with 20 mung beans each. It was an hour of fun, but now Jake and I know just who are the go-to people for accomplishing certain tasks with speed and accuracy!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="news" /><category term="science" /><category term="beetles" /><category term="competition" /><summary type="html">Sport at its finest</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://qgevoeco.github.io/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%22feature-20190424-beetleOlympics.jpg%22,%20%22teaser%22=%3E%2220190424-beetleOlympics.jpg%22,%20%22thumb%22=%3E%22Warlak_siteLogoCard128px.png%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">A visit to Texas Tech</title><link href="https://qgevoeco.github.io/news/spring2019-visit-TTU/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A visit to Texas Tech" /><published>2019-04-18T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-04-18T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://qgevoeco.github.io/news/spring2019-visit-TTU</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://qgevoeco.github.io/news/spring2019-visit-TTU/">&lt;p&gt;I had a wonderful trip to Lubbock, TX to visit my good friends from grad school - &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.depts.ttu.edu/biology/people/faculty/harris/&quot;&gt;Bre Harris&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.depts.ttu.edu/psy/people/zhohman/&quot;&gt;Zach Hohman&lt;/a&gt;. The main purpose was to visit the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.depts.ttu.edu/biology/&quot;&gt;TTU Department of Biological Sciences&lt;/a&gt;, but it is always nice to see some friendly faces in the crowd during your seminar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/Wolak_TTU_titleSlide-600-4b8c57.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Matt presenting at TTU&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/TTU_BuddyHolly-600-400a57.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Outside the Buddy Holly Center&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was fascinating to hear what Bre has been up to since we were together at &lt;a href=&quot;https://eeob.ucr.edu/&quot;&gt;UCR&lt;/a&gt;, particularly I was intriguted by her recent research on stress and fear in &lt;em&gt;Xenopus laevis&lt;/em&gt; frogs - with definite extensions to people! I also learned a whole lot more about the ecology of fire (as well as a great perspective on life in academia) than I ever imagined, from &lt;a href=&quot;http://schwilk.org/&quot;&gt;Dylan Schwilk&lt;/a&gt;. My discussions with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.depts.ttu.edu/biology/people/Faculty/Rice/home/&quot;&gt;Sean Rice&lt;/a&gt;, were very enlightening and they really challenged my understanding of some core quantitative genetic assumptions/practices. I’ll have to keep mulling over the ideas that arose from our dicussing for a while…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, out of the entire trip I’m probably most excited about the lunch I had with graduate students in the TTU DBS. I enjoyed their insightful questions, and it also gave me a chance to mess around before the trip with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gimp.org/&quot;&gt;the GIMP&lt;/a&gt; to produce this fabulously edited photo as the title slide to my talk with the graduate students:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;/images/TheAcademic_AnUnexpectedJourney_WolakPoster.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/TheAcademic_AnUnexpectedJourney_WolakPoster.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;/images/TheHobbitPoster.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/TheHobbitPoster.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;My edited photo on the left versus the real photo on the right.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent far more time working on this than I should have, but it sure was fun learning some photo editing tricks to replace words and faces! Can you spot Bre’s face and my own goofy mug?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="news" /><category term="science" /><category term="travel" /><summary type="html">Fear, frogs, fire, &amp; Buddy Holly: my visit to TTU</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://qgevoeco.github.io/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22TTU_BuddyHolly.jpg%22%7D" /></entry></feed>